Guide to University of Chicago Library Exhibit Publications Collection 1964-2009
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Library. Exhibit Publications. Collection
1964-2009
59 volumes
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The collection includes digitized copies of catalogs and other publications relating to exhibits held at the University of Chicago Library’s Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Digital Images
Original documents, texts, and images represented by digital images linked to this finding aid are subject to U. S. copyright law. It is the user's sole responsibility to secure any necessary copyright permission to reproduce or publish documents, texts, and images from any holders of rights in the original materials.
The University of Chicago Library, in its capacity as owner of the physical property represented by the digital images linked to this finding aid, encourages the use of these materials for educational and scholarly purposes. Any reproduction or publication from these digital images requires that the following credit line be included: Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library.
Commercial publication projects require the permission of the University of Chicago Library and may be subject to a use fee. To order publication-quality reproductions, or for permission to copy or use any part of the digital images attached to this finding aid for any commercial purposes, please contact the Special Collections Research Center.
The images presented here may include materials reflecting the attitudes, language, and stereotypes of an earlier time period. These materials are presented as historical resources in support of study and research. Inclusion of such materials does not constitute an endorsement of their content by the University of Chicago.
The University of Chicago Library appreciates hearing from anyone who may have information about any of the images in this collection.
Scope Note
The collection includes digitized copies of catalogs and other publications relating to exhibits held at the University of Chicago Library’s Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center. Print copies of the publications may be located in the Library Catalog. Some are also available for sale from the Special Collections Research Center.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago Library Special Collections Department, Exhibitions and Conservation (Preservation) Records; Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library.
Subject Headings
University of Chicago; University of Chicago. Library; University of Chicago. Library. Special Collections Research Center; Exhibitions; Exhibition catalogs
INVENTORY
- Scholars and Scholarship of the Renaissance: An Exhibition from the Collections of the University of Chicago Library, As part of a year-long celebration of the Renaissance, this exhibition features selections from the Library's collections that exemplify "a few of the many varieties of scholarly pursuits that marked the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries." The emphasis is on major intellectual and scholarly enterprises. Among the works included are Aristotle, Opera Graece [Venice: Aldus, 1495-98); Joseph Scaliger, De emendatione temporum (Frankfort: Wechelum, 1593), a copy of Demosthenes's Orations (Venice: Aldus, 1504) annotated by Philip Melancthon; Nicholas Copernicus, De Revolutionibus (Nuremberg: I. Petreium, 1543); and Niccol˜ Machiavelli, Discorsi sopra la prima deca di Tito Livio (Rome: A. Blado, 1531). Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1964-December 1, 1964
- Speculum Romanae magnificentiae, No two copies of the Speculum Romanae magnificentiae (Rome: 1575) are alike; the University of Chicago's is the largest compilation known, with over 900 engravings of views and monuments of Classical and early modern Rome. The core of the Speculum was expanded by later owners, resulting in an extraordinary array of beautiful prints that constitute an invaluable historical and artistic resource for the study of Roman life and art. The selections in this exhibition reveal the nature and variety of the collection and the rarity and quality of individual prints. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1966 – December 31, 1966
- Science in nineteenth-century children's books; an exhibition based on the Encyclopaedia Britannica historical collection of books for children in the University of Chicago Library held during the celebration of the University's seventy-fifth anniversary year, August through October, 1966., The 100 books in this exhibition (and listed in the checklist) illustrate the relationship of these books books for children to contemporary scientific and technological advances, the attitudes toward these developments, and the prevailing philosophies and methods of teaching science in the 19th century. Although research in the physical sciences was much greater than in the 18th century, well over half of the science books in the Encylopaedia Britannica Collection are on the biological sciences, reflecting the emphasis on the biological sciences that was typical of 19th-century educational thought. Special Collections Research Center August 1, 1966 – October 31, 1966
- French and Flemish Illuminated Manuscripts from Chicago Collections: An Exhibition in Honor of the 44th Annual Meeting of the Mediaeval Academy of America, Manuscripts from the Newberry Library, the University of Chicago, the Art Institute of Chicago, and private collections were displayed at the Newbery Library in conjunction with the Medieval Society of America. Works included examples of pre-Burgundian illumination, the Vrelant atelier, later Flemish manuscripts, and French manuscripts of the fifteenth and sixteen centuries. Special Collections Research Center April 1, 1969 – May 31, 1969
- Sir Nicholas Bacon Collection, The: Sources on English Society, 1250-1700, The Bacon collection, with its fine chronological series of manorial court and account rolls spanning four centuries, allows one to view the development of English rural and agricultural society in considerable detail. The real strength of the collection lies in the manorial documents relating to Redgrave and Hindercley in Suffolk, both manors in the large ecclesiastical estat4es of the Abbey of Bury St. Edmunds. The present exhibition also serves as the culmination of the efforts of two generations of Chicago scholars beginning with the initiative and foresight of Professors Charles R. Baskerfill, John M. Manly, and Edith Rickert. Special Collections Research Center April 1, 1972 – June 30, 1972
- The Dr. Morris Fishbein Collection: An Exhibition of Selected Books in the History of Medicine and the Biological Sciences, The Morris Fishbein Center for the History of Science and Medicine at the University of Chicago was endowed by Dr. Morris Fishbein, long-time editor of the Journal of the American Medical Association; and his wife, Anna Fishbein. This exhibition features works from the Dr. Morris Fishbein Collection, consisting of books from Dr. Fishbein's personal library and others acquired on an endowed fund that continues to support the purchase of sources to support research and teaching in the history of science and medicine. Among the 98 titles are the 1543 edition of Vesalius's De humani corporis fabrica, Les Oeuvres of Ambroise ParŽ (1575), Descartes, De homine (1662) and Edward Jenner's 1798 treatise on inoculation. Special Collections Research Center October 1, 1972 – January 31, 1973
- Far East: An Exhibition of Resources in the University of Chicago Library, A copy of what scholars believe is the first daily newspaper written by and for women, and published in Peking in the early 1900s, is one of the most recent texts and items of ephemera from East Asia included in this exhibit. The exhibit presents materials written in Chinese, Japanese, Korean, Manchu, Mongolian, and Tibetan. Among the most notable items are a Japanese charm printed in 770 A.D., a 17th century Manchu edition of Chinese ghost stories, and a Tibetan sacred book written in silver ink. The exhibit also includes a section of works written about East Asia by Westerners. This section includes narratives of visits to China by a Russian ambassador and a papal representative in the early 18th century. Documents of Commodore Perry's exhibition to Japan are also included, as are documents and photographs from the visits of two University of Chicago presidents to China. The exhibit represents the breadth of the Library's East Asian holdings, which have developed with the University and the Center for East Asian Studies since the Center's beginnings at the University in the 1930s. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1973 – December 31, 1973
- The Latin Manuscript Book: An Exhibition Selected From the Collections of the University of Chicago Library, This exhibition honors the practice and the tradition of paleography at the University of Chicago. The tradition is a venerable one, extending over many years and several generations of faculty and students. Items on display trace the full history of the Latin manuscript book, including examples of different writing materials, types of manuscripts, scribal techniques, forms of script, readers' notes and marks of ownership, and bindings. Special Collections Research Center July 1, 1973 – Sept. 30, 1973
- Bernard Weinberg, 1909-1973: A Tribute and a Bibliography, The University of Chicago scholar and teacher, Bernard Weinberg, was a textual critic, a literary critic, and an historian of criticism who designated his field of study as "Romance Philology." He was a passionate collector of books in Italian and French literature beginning with a notable array of Renaissance texts on literary criticism. When he completed his work, A History of Literary Criticism in the Italian Renaissance, many of the rare books were given to the Library, and others followed by bequest. This pamphlet was printed on the occasion of an exhibition of Italian and French Books of the Renaissance from the Bequest of Bernard Weinberg. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1974 – December 31, 1974
- Ernest W. Burgess, May 16, 1886-December 27, 1966: An Exhibition of Selections from His Papers, This exhibit reflects the substantial teaching, research, and public service of Ernest W. Burgess. Together with Robert E. Park, Burgess prepared the famous theoretical formulation, Introduction to the Science of Sociology, but he also believed in the importance of life history and human documents as essential tools of sociological investigation. The exhibit traces these themes and also emphasizes the special qualities of Burgess as a teacher. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1974 – December 31, 1974
- The Good Natur'd Man: Oliver Goldsmith; A Bicentennial Celebration, This exhibition honors the scholarship and teaching of Arthur Friedman, distinguished University of Chicago English Department faculty member and editor of The Collected Works of Oliver Goldsmith (Oxford, 1966), the culmination of 30 years of study of the Goldsmith canon. Friedman's work drew on other Goldsmith scholars, including Ronald S. Crane at the University of Chicago. The exhibition suggests the scope of Goldsmith's writings and the nature and complexity of the bibliographical problems his texts present. The selections include Goldmsith's major works in a representative number of editions and minor works that are rare or examples of special bibliographical problems. Special Collections Research Center November 1, 1974 – February 28, 1975
- Charles E. Merriam: An Introduction to the Man and His Papers, Charles E. Merriam (1874-1953) was a political scientist and politician who taught at the University of Chicago from 1900 to 1940 Special Collections Research Center January 1975 - March 1975
- The Norman Wait Harris Memorial Foundation in International Relations, The Norman Wait Harris Memorial Foundation is a trust fund, given to the University of Chicago in 1923, for the promotion of knowledge of an interest in international affairs. The exhibition was a tribute to Harris upon the fiftieth anniversary of the Foundation. Special Collections Research Center Spring 1975
- The Diaghilev Ballet Russes, 1909 - 1929: An Exhibition of Original Designs and Documents, This exhibition was held on the occasion of a dance history seminar funded by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities. In addition to materials from the University of Chicago Library, exhibit items were loaned by the Art Institute of Chicago, Parmenia Migel Ekstrom of New York, the new York Public Library at Lincoln Center, the Stravinsky-Diaghilev Foundation of New York, and the Wadsworth Athaneum of Hartford. Special Collections Research Center July 1, 1975 – October 1, 1975
- The Ludwig Rosenberger Collection of Judaica: A Selection Exhibited at the Joseph Regenstein Library, This exhibition features 126 items from the Rosenberger Collection, which was bequeathed to the University of Chicago Library in 1987. Ludwig Rosenberger collected works documenting the secular life of the Jews in history, literature, and other fields. He emphasized Jewry in western Europe, but also included works on Jews in America and even in China. Works reflecting the relationship of Jews to modern socialism; and the works of certain Jews such as Spinoza, Mendelssohn, Heine, and Marx, are especially well represented in the collection. The selections are arranged in three sections that correspond to emphases in the collection: Pre-Emancipation, 1200-1777; The Enlightenment and Emancipation, 16656-1858; and The Modern World, 1840-1940. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 1976 – May 31, 1976
- Kentucky and the Revolutionary Era, 1770-1815: An Essay Prepared by William T. Hutchinson on the Occasion of an Exhibition of Manuscripts and Early Printed Books from the Reuben T. Durrett Collection, Purchased in 1913, the Reuben T. Durrett Collection was the first major collection relating to American history to be acquired by the University of Chicago Library. Recording the early history of trans-Appalachian settlement of Kentucky and the Ohio River valley, the Durrett collection includes more than 30,000 volumes of printed material, some quite rare; 2,800 holograph manuscripts of early settlers and political leaders; and 50,000 pages of transcriptions of family, legal, and governmental documents, as well as hundreds of newspapers, pamphlets, landplats, maps, clippings, and photographs from the region. Special Collections Research Center November 1, 1976 – February 28, 1978
- Russian and Soviet Studies at the University of Chicago, The tradition of Russian studies at the University of Chicago is almost as old as the University itself. In 1896 Prince Sergei Volkonsky gave a series of lectures on Russian history and Russian institutions and also delivered a convocation address at the University of Chicago. This exhibition traces later developments through the career of Samuel N. Harper and other faculty specialists, the growth of library collections in Russian studies, the formation of the Committee on Slavic Area Studies, and the founding of the Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1977 – December 31, 1977
- The Eighteenth Century Views of the Past, The strong tradition of 18th-century scholarship at the University of Chicago has resulted in deep and rich Library collections. This exhibition, organized in conjunction with the first visit to Chicago of the American Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies, includes historiographical and antiquarian works in the fields of history, literature, art, music, and science. The selections illustrate the 18th century's preoccupation with its own past as a way to understand the present; Adam Smith's An Inquiry Into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations (1776) provides an example of the use of the past for the improvement of the future. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1978 – December 31, 1978
- Anthropology at Chicago: Tradition, Discipline, Department, Marking the fiftieth anniversary of the Department of Anthropology of the University of Chicago, this exhibition displays the archival riches of the Department of Special Collections and suggests how they may be used in the construction of a history--a history of a somewhat unusual type, with special historiographical problems. Materials on display trace anthropology at Chicago from the early work of Frederick Starr through the notable era of Fay-Cooper Cole, Edward Sapir, Robert Redfield, William Lloyd Warner, and A.R. Radcliffe-Brown. Concluding sections review the contributions of Sol Tax, Milton Singer, McKim Marriott, Fred Eggan, Lloyd Fallers, David Schneider, Clifford Geertz, and other leaders of late-twentieth-century American anthropology. Special Collections Research Center January 1, 1979 – December 31, 1979
- The Berlin Collection: Being a History and Exhibition of the Books and Manuscripts Purchased in Berlin in 1891 for the University of Chicago by William Rainey Harper with the Support of Nine Citizens of Chicago, The collection of nearly 100,000 books and manuscripts purchased by William Rainey Harper in Berlin in 1891 became the core of the University of Chicago Library's holdings and have had an abiding influence on the course of scholarly investigation at the University. The Library's collections of incunabula and manuscripts had their beginning with the Berlin Collection, but the real impact came from books printed during the later Renaissance and into the eighteenth century. In one stroke, as it were, the Library had books on many subjects, some of which were not to become academically favored for decades to come, for example those in the history of science and technology. Special Collections Research Center Jan. 1, 1979 – Dec. 31, 1979
- Poetry Magazine: A Gallery of Voices, This exhibition draws mainly on the unique historical portion of the Harriet Monroe Modern Poetry Collection, an archive of the tens of thousands of letters and manuscripts Monroe collected exchanged with poets and collected during her tenure as editor of Poetry Magazine. This exhibit of remarkable material presents the first appearances of great works such as T.S. Eliot's "The Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock," William Carlos William's "Love Song," and Ezra Pound's "Cantos." The manuscripts show the poets' own hands, their writing process, and in them, the tangible remains of the birth of modernist poetry. Though the exhibit does not do justice to Monroe's tremendous efforts in managing the magazine, it focuses on the poets themselves, and the role the magazine itself, and the work of publication, played in creating modernist poetry. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1980 – October 1, 1980
- The Human Fabric: Anatomical Illustration from 1500 to 1850, The title of this exhibition is taken from Andreas Vesalius' consummate work on human anatomy first published in 1543, De humani corporis fabrica. Representing the major themes of this exhibit, Vesalius' work seeks to blend scientific accuracy with high aesthetic standards. This adaptation of well-established artistic traditions to the requirements of a new science occasionally resulted in an uneasy combination in which the creative impulses of the illustrator competed with less subjective interests of the anatomist-scientist. This tension presents a striking array of images that blur the boundaries of art and science. The Human Fabric follows the development of anatomical illustration in print from its beginning as a primitive record of early explorations in gross anatomy in the late fifteenth century to the highly refined studies published just prior to the advent of photography. The books in this exhibition are drawn chiefly from the collection of Dr. Mortimer Frank (1847-1919), a Chicago Physician and Hyde Park resident. Special Collections Research Center February - April, 1981
- The Printer's Craft: An Exhibition Selected from the R.R. Donnelley and Sons Company Collection, When it came time to dissolve its Training Department Library, R.R. Donnelley and Sons Company decided to donate the books to two libraries, the Newberry Library and the University of Chicago Library, both libraries with longstanding interests in the history of printing. In deference to the Newberry's notable emphasis on the subject it was given first choice. The University of Chicago acquired the remaining 1,200 volumes, greatly enriching its holdings in the history of fine printing. The Training Department Library from which these books came was intimately connected to the Donnelley Company's pioneering commitment to apprenticeship training in printing. With its stress on classroom instruction, supervised training, and access to a well-stocked library, the Donnelly program represented a high point in industrial training in the United States. The R.R. Donnelley and Sons collection, now housed in the Special Collections Research Center-like the library from which it was drawn-is composed of two parts, one of finely printed books, the other of books on printing and design. This exhibit celebrates the acquisition of the R.R. Donnelley and Sons Collection with a representative sample of books and printer's tools illustrating both the intricacy of the printer's craft, and the close relationship between industrial training, the continuing development of printing as a craft and trade, and Chicago itself. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1982 – September 1, 1982
- Splendid Encounters: The Thought and Conduct of Diplomacy, Long the preserve of specialists and politicians, diplomacy is being rediscovered as a subject for general scholarly inquiry and debate. This exhibit-and the book produced in association with it-offer a fresh look at aspects of diplomacy that are usually ignored but which give the activity its distinctive style. Iconography, the role of ceremony, and the demands of honor, are all considered along with cryptology, protocol, and the clash of cultural norms. The practice of diplomacy is then set against the Western intellectual tradition in such a way as to re-establish the links between thought and conduct. The exhibit draws on the rare book and manuscript collections held by the University of Chicago Library. Special Collections Research Center May 1, 1984 – September 1, 1984